Diana Villasana Ocampo

POPULATION RESEARCHER ACTUARIAL SCIENCE | STATITICS

Mexico City, Mexico

▼ dvillasanao@hotmail.com | ☑ dvillasanao | ऻ dvillasanao | У dvillasanao

SUMMARY_

Statistician specialist with skills and experience in demographic planning for the development of public policies at the national level. Among the activities conducted on a daily are the provision of specialized technical advice to different federal and local public administration agencies; as well as the updating and management of surveys, censuses, and vital statistics for the generation of socio-demographic diagnoses and research topics.

EDUCATION

Applied Statistics

ANAHUAC UNIVERSITY

Actuarial Science

ANAHUAC UNIVERSITY

Evaluation of the Public Policies and Programs

UED – SECRETARIAT OF FINANCE AND PUBLIC CREDIT (SHCP)

Master degree

2018 - 2020

Bachelor degree

2010 - 2015

Diploma Course

Sepetember 2023

WORK HISTORY ___

Head of Internal Migration Department

Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL POPULATION COUNCIL (CONAPO)

2017 - Present

- Developed and executed research projects on marginalization, poverty, vulnerability, internal migration, general mobility, internal displacement, and related socio-demographic indicators to inform demographic planning in the country, resulting in evidence-based policy recommendations and interventions.
- Researched and analyzed population and development data from diverse sources, resulting in the creation of comprehensive technical responses utilized by federal public administration agencies to inform decision-making and policy development, driving effective resource allocation, and promoting sustainable development outcomes.

Achivements

- Methodological improvements in the scheme of the Marginalization Index in all the different levels of geographical disaggregation are key to the social policies and government programs of the country
- Evaluate the quality of the environment in issues of equipment for the Official Mexican Standards for Certification of Disability (PROY-NOM-039-SSA-2023).
- Implementation of the Odisea | Mexico platform in collaboration with the United Nations Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean (ECLAC) of the Population Division of CELADE. (Link: https://odisea.redatam.org/mex/).

Assistant in the Internal Migration Department

Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL POPULATION COUNCIL (CONAPO)

January 2016 - July 2016

- Conducted research on internal migration laws and policies to ensure compliance and accuracy.
- Database management and analysis on migration, marginalization, and socio-demographic indicators.

Coordination assistant of Risk Department

Mexico City, Mexico

RURAL FINANCIAL

January 2010 - November

• Provided administrative support to the coordination team, including document preparation, data entry, and file management.

• Assisted in coordinating and monitoring risk management activities to ensure compliance with company policies.



Hard Skills

Sampling and Census Survey Data Mining Machine Learning Data Visualization

Public Policy Policy Evaluation

Language

HTML CSS LaTeX Git Markdown

Soft Skills

Project Management Verbal Communication Writting Communication Public Communication

Software Skills

R
Python
SPSS Statistics
SAS
STATA
ArcGIS
SQL
PowerBI | DAX
Visual Studio Code

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. CONAPO. (2023). Environment quality index 2020. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2023*, 57–78. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/856497/LSDM23_Completo.pdf
- 2. SEDATU, CONAPO, & INEGI. (2023). Metropolises of mexico 2020. *Joint Project of the Secretariat of Agrarian, Territorial and Urban Development (SEDATU), the National Population Council (CONAPO), and the National Institute of Statistics and Geography (INEGI)*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/sedatu/documentos/metropolis-de-mexico-2020?state=published.
- 3. CONAPO. (2023). Conceptual and methodological changes of marginalization indices 2020. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2022*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/783840/SDM_Parte9.pdf.
- 4. CONAPO. (2022). Diagnosis on the situation of internal forced displacement in mexico. *Internal Forced Displacement in Mexico: From the Recognition of Challenges*, 25–35. Available at: http://www.alejandroencinas.mx/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/DESPLAZAMIENTO-FORZADO-INTERNO-EN-MEXICO-PDF.pdf
- 5. CONAPO. (2022). *National diagnosis about internal forced displacement in mexico*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/diagnostico-nacional-sobre-la-sitacion-del-desplazamiento-forzado-interno-en-mexico
- 6. CONAPO. (2022). Recent internal return migration in mexico. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2021*, 125–147. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/la-situacion-demografica-de-mexico-2021
- 7. CONAPO. (2021). *Index of marginalization by locality 2020*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-demarginacion-2020-284372
- 8. CONAPO. (2021). *Index of marginalization by AGEB 2020*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-demarginacion-2020-284372
- 9. CONAPO. (2021). Index of marginalization by state and municipality 2020. Available at https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-de-marginacion-2020-284372
- 10. CONAPO. (2019). The equipment in the urbanized areas of mexico, 2018. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2019*, 109–131. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/la-situacion-demografica-de-mexico-2019
- 11. CONAPO. (2019). Sociodemographic profile of the population that changed their home or place of residence to protect themselves from crime. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/514162/PERFIL_SOCIODEMOGRAFICO_final_ISBN.pdf.
- 12. CONAPO. (2019). Student mobility in mexico. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2018*, 124–141. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/491898/p124-p141.pdf.
- 13. CONAPO, & UNFPA. (2019). Violence as a cause of forced internal displacement, approaches to its analysis in mexico. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/es/documentos/la-violencia-como-causa-de-desplazamiento-interno-forzado-aproximaciones-a-su-analisis-en-mexico?state=published
- 14. SEDATU, & CONAPO. (2018). *National urban system 2018*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/sistema-urbano-nacional-2018
- 15. CONPO. (2016). *Index of marginalization by federal entity and municipality 2015*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/459282/00_Preliminares.pdf.
- 16. SEDATU, CONAPO, & INEGI. (2016). Delimitation of the metropolitan areas of mexico 2015. In *Joint project of the Secretariat of Agrarian, Territorial, and Urban Development (SEDATU), the National Population Council (CONAPO), and the National Institute of Statistics and Geography (INEGI)*. Available at: https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/delimitacion-de-las-zonas-metropolitanas-de-mexico-2015